Inventory of the Cabell Family Papers 1693-1913, 1743-1823
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Papers, 1693-1913, n.d. (Box 1-9)
  - George Gilmer, Penn Park, to Col. William Cabell, 26 Jan. 1792., ALS. (Box-folder 3:6)
    Item is giving medical advice.
  - Legal papers and accounts of Col. William Cabell, Jun[io]r, 1792., ADsS. (Box-folder 3:6)
  - Landon Cabell, Kingston, Jamaica, to his brother William Cabell, 2 Sept. 1792., ALS. (Box-folder 3:6)
    Item explains why he will not return home from Jamaica and stating, "I live, I repent and will atone, as far as a future life of self denial, and a steady observance of all that is right can atone for my misdeeds."
  - John Nicholas, Charlottesville, to William Cabell, Junior, 13 Oct. 1792., ALS. (Box-folder 3:6)
    Item concerns Cabell's candidacy for U.S. Representative.
  - W[illiam] Cabell, Union Hill, to Landon Cabell, Kingston, Jamaica., Cy of ALS. (Box-folder 3:6)
    Itemis requesting Landon Cabell to return home.
  - Account of Col. Joseph Cabell, with note signed by John Breckinridge. 31 Dec. 1792., ADS. (Box-folder 3:6)
  - Accounts, receipts, and legal papers, 1793., ADsS. (Box-folder 3:7)
  - Prescription by Dr. Gilmer, 19 Aug. 1793., L. (Box-folder 3:7)
  - George Gilmer, Pen Park, to Col. William Cabell, 24 Aug. 1793., ALS. (Box-folder 3:7)
    Item concerns his family's health.
  - James Pleasants, J[unio]r, Goochland, to William Crawford, Amherst, 26 Oct. 1793., ALS. (Box-folder 3:7)
    Item talks about subscriptions to his relative Mr. Pleasant's paper which is "entirely friendly to Republicanism and the cause of France... ."
  - Legal papers and receipts, 1794., ADsS. (Box-folder 3:8)
  - George Hancock, Philadelphia, to William S. Crawford, Amherst County, of Virginia, 13 Feb. 1794., ALS. (Box-folder 3:8)
    Item concerns legislation in the U.S. Congress.
  - Charge to the Grand Jury, March 1794, and Aug. 1794., AD. (Box-folder 3:8)
  - Accounts, letters relating to land transactions, and surveys signed by Ja[me]s Higginbothan, surveyor, 1795., ADsS and ALsS. (Box-folder 3:9)
  - Landon Cabell to Col. William Cabell, 23 Nov. 1795., ALS. (Box-folder 3:9)
    Item concerns business matters.
  - Accounts, receipts, and legal papers, 1796., ADsS. (Box-folder 3:10)
  - J. Breckinridge, Fayette, to William S. Crawford, Amherst, 8 April 1796., ALS. (Box-folder 3:10)
  - William H. Cabell, Richmond, to Col. William Cabell, 14 Nov. 1796 and 18 Nov. 1796., ALsS.. (Box-folder 3:10)
    Item mentions legal advice given by [John] Marshall.
  - "Memo of shoes, stockings & blankets gave my Negroes," 27 Nov. 1796., AD. (Box-folder 3:10)
  - Accounts and receipts, 1797., ADs and ADsS. (Box-folder 3:11)
  - Accounts and receipts, 1798., ADsS. (Box-folder 4:1)
  - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, to William S. Crawford Esq[r]., attorney at law, Amherst, 26 Sept. 1798., ALS. (Box-folder 4:1)
    Item concerns resuming his practice in the superior court and engaging in the business you mention.
  - Letters from William H. Cabell (1772-1853) about the division of the county to William S. Crawford and [?], 13 Dec. 1798, 17 Dec. 1798, and 21 Dec. 1798. ALsS. (Box-folder 4:1)
  - Letters from William H. Cabell (1772-1853) about the division of the county to William S. Crawford and [?], 13 Dec. 1798, 17 Dec. 1798, and 21 Dec. 1798., ALsS. (Box-folder 4:1)
  - Accounts and receipts, 1799., ADs and ADsS. (Box-folder 4:2)
  - Survey signed by Ja[me]s Higginbotham, surveyor, 1800., ADS. (Box-folder 4:3)
  - Phillip Norbonne Nicholas, Richmond, to William S. Crawford,, about the selection of electors. 12 Sept. 1800., ALS. (Box-folder 4:3)
    Item concerns the selection of electors.
  - W. B. Ha[re], [delegate from Amherst Co.], Richmond, to William S. Crawford, Amherst, 3 Dec. 1800., ALS. (Box-folder 4:3)
    Saying all the electors will vote for Jefferson and Burr.
  - Receipts and surveys signed by Ja[me]s C. Higginbothan, asst. surveyor, 1801., ADs and ADsS. (Box-folder 4:4)
  - Business correspondence, 1801., ALsS. (Box-folder 4:4)
  - J[oh]n Camm, Richmond, to William S. Crawford, Cabellsburg, Amherst Co., Virginia,, 26 Dec. 1802., ALS. (Box-folder 4:5)
    Mentions the work of the current session of the House of Delegates and the dispute which took place between George Hay and James Thompson Callender.
  - Business correspondence of William S. Crawford, 1803., ALsS. (Box-folder 4:6)
  - Tho[ma]s M. Randolph, Albemarle, to William Crawford, Clerk of Amherst Co, Virginia, 16 July 1803., ALS. (Box-folder 4:6)
    Item concerns a request for a copy of the Amherst polls for Representative in Congress and commenting on international news.
  - J[oh]n Camm, Richmond, to William S. Crawford, Amherst County, 29 Dec. 1803., ALS. (Box-folder 4:6)
    Item gives news of the House of Delegates.
  - Receipts and papers of W[illia]m H. Cabell and William S. Crawford, 1804., ADsS. (Box-folder 4:7)
  - William B. Hare, Midway, to Col. William Cabell, 26 April 1804., AL. Signature clipped. (Box-folder 4:7)
    Item concerns a promise of a loan.
  - William B. Hare, Midway, to Capt. Edward Carter, 22 Dec. 1804., ALS. (Box-folder 4:7)
  - William B. Hare, Midway, to [?], 22 Dec. 1804., ALS. (Box-folder 4:7)
  - List of books purchased by P[atrick] Henry from his father's estate contained in a letter from E. Winston to Col. William Cabell, 30 Oct. 1804., AD and ALS. (Box-folder 4:7)
  - Receipts of Col. William Cabell, 1805., ADsS. (Box-folder 4:8)
  - E. Winston, Huntingtour, to Col. William Cabell,, 16 Jan. 1805., ALS. (Box-folder 4:8)
    Item deals with the settlement of the estate of P[atrick] Henry.
  - Printed notice of Thomas M. Randolph about Mr. Leake of Albemarle who hopes to take his place in the House of Representatives, 21 Jan. 1805., D. (Box-folder 4:8)
  - Fayette Henry, Lynchburg, to Col. William Cabell, 17 April 1805., ALS. (Box-folder 4:8)
    Item talks about the preaching of his deceased brother's funeral sermon.
  - Landon Cabell to Col. William Cabell, 5 May 1805., ALS. (Box-folder 4:8)
  - William Jordan Cabell, Washington Academy, to his father William Cabell, 23 June 1805., ALS. (Box-folder 4:8)
    Item concerns William Jordan Cabell's [lottery?] tickets.
  - E. Winston, Huntingtour, to Col. William Cabell, 5 Aug. 1805., ALS. (Box-folder 4:8)
  - Notes about Mr. Henry's estate, 29 Jan. 1806., AD. (Box-folder 4:9)
  - Legal papers of William Cabell., ADsS. (Box-folder 4:9)
  - William Jordan Cabell, Washington Academy, to his father William Cabell, 26 March 1806., ALS. (Box-folder 4:9)
    Letter talks about William Jordan Cabell's debts.
  - William H. Cabell, Richmond, to Col. William Cabell, 29 April 1806, ALS. (Box-folder 4:9)
    Letter talks about the sale of his tobacco.
  - William H. Cabell, Richmond, to Col. William Cabell, 13 May 1806., ALS. (Box-folder 4:9)
  - William H. Cabell, Richmond, to Col. William Cabell, 20 May 1806., ALS. (Box-folder 4:9)
  - William H. Cabell, Richmond, to Col. William Cabell, 30 May 1806., ALS. (Box-folder 4:9)
  - William H. Cabell, Richmond, to Col. William Cabell, 24 June 1806., ALS. (Box-folder 4:9)
  - William H. Cabell, Richmond, to Col. William Cabell, 29 July 1806., ALS. (Box-folder 4:9)
  - William H. Cabell, Richmond, to Col. William Cabell, 12 Aug. 1806., ALS. (Box-folder 4:9)
  - William J. Cabell, Washington Academy, to his father Col. William Cabell, 11 Aug. 1806., ALS. (Box-folder 4:9)
    Letter talks about his family's health and his studies.
  - William H. Cabell, Richmond, to Col. William Cabell, 1 Sept. 1806., ALS. (Box-folder 4:9)
    Letter talks about the settlement of Mr. Henry's debts.
  - Public notice, 10 Sept. 1806., AD. (Box-folder 4:9)
    Notice talks about the opening of "a public school" in the New Glasgow Academy.
  - Paulina Read to her brother William Cabell, Sen[io]r, 22 Nov,. 1806 and 21 Dec. 1806., ALsS. (Box-folder 4:9)
    Letter talks about the management of her slaves--probably selling Frank because he has no connections nearby or hiring him out to "some humane person that will treat him well."
  - Accounts of William Cabell, 1807., ADs and ADsS. (Box-folder 5:1)
  - William H. Cabell, Richmond, to Col. William Cabell, 20 Oct. 1807 and 1 Nov. 1807., ALS and AL. Signature clipped. (Box-folder 5:1)
  - Reuben Crawford, Shelbyville, to his brother Charles Crawford, Amherst Co., Virginia, 23 Oct. 1807 and 15 Nov. 1807., ALsS. (Box-folder 5:1)
  - W[ilson] C[ary] Nicholas, Washington, D. C., [House of Representatives], to William Crawford, Amherst Courthouse, Virginia, 6 Dec. 1707 [1807]., ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
    Letter concernc the negotiations with the British government.
  - William B. Hare, Richmond, to Col. William Cabell, 22 Dec. 1807., ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
  - William H. Cabell to the Court of Amherst, 1808., ALS. (Box-folder 5:2)
  - Elizabeth Crawford, Amherst County, to "my dear son," 9 April 1808., ALS. (Box-folder 5:2)
  - William H. Cabell, Richmond, to Col. William Cabell, 22 June 1808.ALS., ALS. (Box-folder 5:2)
  - Landon Cabell to his brother Col. William Cabell, 26 June 1808., ALS. (Box-folder 5:2)
  - Landon Cabell's deposition, 29 Oct. 1808., ADS. (Box-folder 5:2)
    Deposition concerns a negro runaway slave name Fleming.
  - Accounts, 1809., ADs and ADsS. (Box-folder 5:3)
  - Dabney Carr, Charlottesville, to William S. Crawford, Amherst, 2 Feb. 1809., ALS. (Box-folder 5:3)
  - Accounts, 1810., ADsS. (Box-folder 5:4)
  - William B. Hare, Richmond, to Col. William Cabell, 24 May 1810., ALS. (Box-folder 5:4)
  - William H. Cabell to Col. William Cabell, 31 May 1810 and 22 Dec. 1810., ALsS. (Box-folder 5:4)
  - David S. Garland, Washington, D.C., to William S. Crawford, Amherst County, Virginia, 27 Jan. 1811., ALS. (Box-folder 5:5)
    Letter concerns the happenings in the House of Representatives.
  - David S. Garland, City [of Washington] to [?], n.d., ALS. (Box-folder 5:5)
  - David S. Garland, City of Wash[ington] to [?], 26 Feb. 1811., ALS. (Box-folder 5:5)
  - William H. Cabell to [?], 14 Aug. 1811., ALS. (Box-folder 5:5)
  - William H. Cabell, Monte Video, to Col. William Cabell, 18 Aug. 1811., ALS. (Box-folder 5:5)
  - Joseph C. Cabell, Edgewood, to Col. William Cabell, 17 Aug. 1811., ALS. (Box-folder 5:5)
    Letter mentions that Mr. Tucker and he will come to dinner.
  - Joseph C. Cabell, Edgewood, to Col. William Cabell, 18 Aug. 1811., AL. Signature clipped. (Box-folder 5:5)
  - William H. Hare, Richmond, to [?], 17 Dec. 1811., ALS. (Box-folder 5:5)
  - Accounts, 1812., ADs and ADsS. (Box-folder 5:6)
  - Joseph C. Cabell, Richmond, to Col. William Cabell, 6 Jan. 1812., ALS. (Box-folder 5:6)
  - Accounts, receipts, and business correspondence, 1813., ADsS and ALsS. (Box-folder 5:6)
  - Accounts, 1814., ADsS. (Box-folder 6:1)
  - Business letters written to William S. Crawford., ALsS. (Box-folder 6:1)
  - Joseph C. Cabell, Richmond, to Mr. and Mrs. McLelland, 7 Dec. 1814., ALS. (Box-folder 6:1)
  - Joseph C. Cabell, Richmond, to Col. William Cabell, 29 Dec. 1814., ALS. (Box-folder 6:1)
  - Will[iam] Cabell, List of property, 1815., AD. (Box-folder 6:2)
  - Joseph C. Cabell, Edgewood, to Col. William Cabell, 11 Feb. 1815. (Box-folder 6:2)
  - Joseph C. Cabell, Edgewood, to Col. William Cabell, 4 March 1815., ALS. (Box-folder 6:2)
  - Accounts and receipts, 1816., ADs and ADsS. (Box-folder 6:3)
  - Tho[ma]s Hawkins to Col. William Cabell, 20 Oct. 1816., ALS. (Box-folder 6:3)
    Letter concerns the clothing of Negroes.
  - Accounts and business papers, 1817., ADs and ADsS. (Box-folder 6:4)
  - [Paul Carrington, Sr.] to Col. William Cabell, 25 March 1817., AL. Signature clipped. (Box-folder 6:4)
    Letter concern "the family of Hannah I mean the two girls [who] have never been House servants, other then as spinners, at [which] business they have been excellent hands and may yet be so, if taught a proper degree of subordination by a mistress--the others except the small children have been wraught in the plantation,"
  - Business papers, 1818., ADsS and ALsS. (Box-folder 6:5)
  - Joseph C. Cabell, Edgewood, to [St. George Tucker], 3 July 1818., ALS. (Box-folder 6:5)
    Letter states that his "negroes are now under excellent discipline and so free from punishment & so well satisfied with their situation, that my carpenter John Brown, who must be sent to Corrottoman this fall, is very much opposed to going although I consent for his wife to go with him. My overseer is an active, attentive, & amiable man."
  - Joseph C. Cabell, Edgewood, to [St. George Tucker], 28 Oct. 1818., ALS. (Box-folder 6:5)
    Letter conerns the difficulty of hiring a new overseer.
  - Business correspondence, 1819., ADs, ADsS, and ALsS. (Box-folder 6:6)
  - William H. Cabell, Monte Video, to Col. William Cabell, 22 Nov. 1818., ALS. (Box-folder 6:6)
  - Business correspondence and receipts, 1820., ADs, ADsS, and ALsS. (Box-folder 6:7)
  - William H. Cabell to Col. William Cabell, 17 Sept. 1820., ALS. (Box-folder 6:7)
    Letter concerns business matters.
  - S.C. Cabell to Papa [Col. William Cabell], 6 Nov. 1820., ALS. (Box-folder 6:7)
    Letter concerns news at "Union Grove."
  - Joseph C. Cabell, Richmond, to Col. William Cabell, 8 Feb. 1821., ALS. (Box-folder 6:8)
    Letter conerns his plans to be a candidate for the Senate.
  - Joseph C. Cabell, Edgewood, to Dr. George Callaway, 19 Oct. 1821., ALS. (Box-folder 6:8)
    Letter conerns business matters.
  - Accounts and business correspondence., ADs, ADsS, and ALsS. (Box-folder 6:8)
  - Business correspondence, 1822., ADs, ADsS, and ALsS. (Box-folder 6:9)
  - Joseph C. Cabell, Warminster, to St. George Tucker, 7 June 1823., ALS. (Box-folder 6:10)
    Letter concerns family and business matters.
  - A bill of jobs for Mrs. Callay., AD. (Box-folder 6:10)
  - Manuscript volume of essays dated Richmond, Virginia, 7 June 1828., MsV. 1. (Box-folder 6:11)
  - Plat of 144 acres, Nelson County, belonging to Charles Flood, signed by W[illia]m Hill, asst. surveyor, 31 Aug. 1829., ADS. (Box-folder 6:12)
  - Receipt, 1 May 1830., AD. (Box-folder 7:1)
  - Creed Taylor to W[illia]m Long, 24 Dec. 1831., ALS. (Box-folder 7:1)
    Letter conerns hiring his man Joshua.
  - Business papers, 1834., ALS and ADS. (Box-folder 7:1)
  - Business letter, 19 Nov. 1837., AL. (Box-folder 7:2)
  - Account of Robert L. Brown with James Smiley, 1838., AD. (Box-folder 7:2)
  - Small manuscript volume of surveying notes made for William Horsley, 23 Jan. 1839 and 21 Feb. 1839., MsV. 2. (Box-folder 7:2)
  - Field notes of land surveyed for George W. Smiley, 1840., AD. (Box-folder 7:3)
  - Field notes surveyed for James W. Smiley, 1841., AD. (Box-folder 7:3)
  - Field notes surveyed for William A. Payne, 1841., AD. (Box-folder 7:3)
  - Field notes surveyed for Thomas Carter, 1841., AD. (Box-folder 7:3)
  - Business papers, 1843., AD and ADsS. (Box-folder 7:3)
  - Receipt, 1844., ADS. (Box-folder 7:3)
  - Receipt and business letters, 1845., AD and ALsS. (Box-folder 7:3)
  - Accounts and surveys, 1846., ADs and ADsS. (Box-folder 7:4)
  - Accounts and surveys, 1847., ADs and ADsS. (Box-folder 7:4)
  - Accounts and surveys, 1848., ADs and ADsS. (Box-folder 7:4)
  - Accounts and surveys, 1851., ADs and ADsS. (Box-folder 7:4)
  - Accounts and surveys, 1852., ADs and ADsS. (Box-folder 7:4)
  - Accounts and surveys, 1853., ADs and ADsS. (Box-folder 7:4)
  - Accounts and business correspondence, 1854-1856., ADsS and ALsS. (Box-folder 7:5)
  - Accounts of Mayo Cabell with Isaac R. Watkins, 1856., MsV. 3. (Box-folder 7:5)
  - Accounts and business correspondence, 1857-1862., ADs, ADsS, and ALsS. (Box-folder 7:6)
    Items include accounts of Robert L. Brown and Mayo Cabell and business letters of Mayo Cabell.
  - Business correspondence, 1867., ALsS. (Box-folder 7:7)
  - Business correspondence of Alexander Brown, 1876-1878., ALsS. (Box-folder 7:7)
  - Accounts and memoranda, 1879., ADsS. (Box-folder 7:7)
  - Business correspondence of Alexander Brown and copies of his letters relating to his history of the colony of Virginia, 1880-1886., ALsS. (Box-folder 7:7)
  - Accounts of Miss Lucy G. Cabell, 1911-1913., ADsS. (Box-folder 7:7)
  - Letters, arranged alphabetically by signature, n.d., 42 items. ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - M.B. Brown, n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - Ja[me]s Murray Brown, n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - W[illia]m Brown, n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - Geo[rge] Cabell, Jr., n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - Capt. Hector Cabill [Cabell], n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - Nicholas Cabell, n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - N. Cabell, Jr., n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - Sam[uel] J. Cabell, n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - Cal. S. J. Cabell, n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - W[illia]m D. Cabell, n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - W[illia]m H. Cabell, n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - W[illia]m J. Cabell, n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - L. Cally, n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - Cdm. Carrington, n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - C. Carrington, n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - Thomas W. Cooke, n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - Reuben Crawford, n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - Nicho[las] Daviss, n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - S. Garland, n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - Tho[ma]s Goodwin, n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - Sam[ue]l Hansbrough, n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - Ja[me]s Ingram, n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - Lawrence Long, n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - Will Long, n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - J[oh]n Loving, n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - Tho[mas] McCleland, n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - Peters Martin & Co., n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - Tho[mas] Moore, n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - E. Penn, n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - Col. Gabriel Penn, n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - J. Penn, n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - Tho[ma]s Penn, n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - Geo[rge] Perkins, n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - John Phillips, n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - R. Rives, n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - Eliza[beth] Rose, n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - W. Spencer, n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - Smyth Tandy, n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - John Timberlake, n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - Sam[ue]l Venable, n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - W[illia]m Warwick, n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - John Watkins, n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 8:1)
  - Undated and lost correspondence, n.d., ALs. (Box-folder 8:2)
  - Livestock on various farms, n.d., ADs. (Box-folder 8:3)
  - List of books belonging to the estate of William Cabell. n.d., AD. (Box-folder 8:4)
  - Lists of slaves, n.d., ADs. (Box-folder 8:5)
  - Legal documents, n.d., ADs and ADsS. (Box-folder 8:6)
  - Papers relating to the James Dickie dispute, n.d., ADs and ADS. (Box-folder 8:7)
  - Religious writings, n.d., AMsS. (Box-folder 8:8)
  - Prescriptions, n.d., ADs. (Box-folder 8:9)
  - Undated accounts, legal papers, and surveys, n.d., ADs and ADsS. (Box-folder 8:10)
  - Biography of Col. W[illia]m Cabell, Sr., n.d., AMsS. (Box-folder 8:11)
  - Autographs before 1799. n.d. (Box-folder 8:12)
  - Signatures, n.d. (Box-folder 8:13)
  - Broadside "John W. Barnett's Tobacco Curing! Process," n.d. (Box-folder 8:14)
  - Notes on historical source material, n.d., Ms. (Box-folder 8:15)
  - Invoices and receipts, including a list of medicines sold, n.d., ADs and ADsS. (Box-folder 8:16)
  - Photographs of portraits, 6 items. Photographs. (Box-folder 8:17)
    - Col. Will[iam] Cabell, Jr., 1808., 1 item. Photograph. (Box-folder 8:17)
    - W[illia]m Cabell (?), 1808., 1 item. Photograph. (Box-folder 8:17)
    - Nicholas Cabell, Jr., n.d., 1 item. Photograph. (Box-folder 8:17)
    - Brown relatives in Australia, n.d., 2 items. Photographs. (Box-folder 8:17)
    - Joseph Carrington Cabell, 1804., 1 item. Photograph. (Box-folder 8:17)
  - Copies of historical and genealogical manuscripts and printed material made by Alexander Brown and others, n.d., Copies. Ms. (Box-folder 9:1)
  - Notices of books by Alexander Brown, n.d., Printed material. (Box-folder 9:2)
  - Copies of militia rolls, 1775-1776., Copies. Ms. (Box-folder 9:3)
  - Copies of partial lists of tithables of the upper part of St. Anne's Parish, Albemarle, n.d., Copies. Ms. (Box-folder 9:4)
  - Copies of surveys, n.d., Copies. Cy of ADSs. (Box-folder 9:5-6)
  - Clipping from the Standard, about a letter from John Brown to W[illia]m Cabell dated 20 April 1781. Nov. 23, 1878., NCl. (Box-folder 9:7)
  - Survey, n.d., AD. (Box-folder 9:8)
  - Fragments of printed material. n.d. (Box-folder 9:9)
  - Miscellaneous pages from The Journal of the House of Delegates, n.d. (Box-folder 9:10)
  - Typescript of historical article by Alexander Brown, n.d., Typescript. (Box-folder 9:11)
  - Fragments, n.d. (Box-folder 9:12-13)
  Series 2: Manuscripts
- Manuscripts 1736-1878, n.d., MsV.
  - Manuscript volume of essays dated Richmond, Virginia, 7 June 1828., MsV. 1. (Box-folder 6:11)
  - Small manuscript volume of surveying notes made for William Horsley, 23 Jan. 1839 and 21 Feb. 1839., MsV. 2. (Box-folder 7:2)
  - Accounts of Mayo Cabell with Isaac R. Watkins, 1856., MsV. 3. (Box-folder 7:5)
  - Field survey book of Dr. William Cabell, n.d., MsV. 4-5. (Box 10)
  - Notebook including merchants' arithmetic problems by Nicholas Cabell, 1750-1779., 22 pages. MsV. 6. (Box 10)
  - Entry survey book of Col. William Cabell (1729/30-1798), who became asst. surveyor of Albemarle County in 1753, June 25-Oct. 7, 1753., 13 pages. MsV. 7. (Box 10)
  - Entry survey book for Goochland County, a few entries in William Cabell's hand, 1736-1743., 32 pages. MsV. 8. (Box 10)
    These are not complete entries--i.e. 101, 114, 214, etc., and may have been written by Dr. William Cabell after he returned from England in 1741.
  - Entry survey book in several hands for Albemarle County, Dec. 144-April 1745., 120 pages. MsV. 9. (Box 10)
  - Entry survey book in unknown hand with index, 1743-1747., MsV. 10. (Box 10)
  - Entry survey book of Dr. William Cabell, 1743., MsV. 11. (Box 10)
  - Account book including farm and medical accounts of Dr. William Cabell, 1752-1774., MsV. 12. (Box 10)
  - Field book of Dr. William Cabell with written religious reflections in an unknown hand, probably 17th century, 1752-1754., 318 pages. MsV. 13. (Box 10)
  - Religious notes in unknown hand interleaved with surveys, one in the hand of William Cabell, Jr., 1756-1758., MsV. 14. (Box 11)
    Notes on medicine, tobacco, and farm accounts are by Dr. William Cabell.
  - Notebook containing mathematical problems in an unknown hand, n.d., MsV. 15. (Box 11)
  - Field book of Dr. William Cabell, n.d., MsV. 16. (Box 11)
  - Field and entry book of Dr. William Cabell with shorthand explanation for religious notes, n.d., MsV. 17. (Box 11)
  - Field book of Dr. William Cabell's with religious notes in unknown hand, n.d., MsV. 18. (Box 11)
  - Loose back of surveyor's notebook, n.d., MsV. 19. (Box 11)
  - Entry survey book of Dr. William Cabell, n.d., MsV. 20. (Box 11)
  - Entry survey book for several surveyors, probably including Joshua Fry,., MsV. 21. (Box 11)
  - Field survey book of Dr. William Cabell, n.d., MsV. 22. (Box 11)
  - Field survey book of Dr. William Cabell, 1743., MsV. 23. (Box 11)
  - Field survey book of Dr. William Cabell, 1749-1751., MsV. 24. (Box 11)
  - W. S. Crawford's District Docket to September Court, 1790., 26 pages. MsV. 25. (Box 12)
  - W. L. Crawford's notebook containing list of cases that came up in Court, Sept. 1791., 20 pages. MsV. 26 (Box 12)
  - Crawford's notebook of District Docket to the Court, Sept. 1792., 15 pages. MsV. 27. (Box 12)
  - Notebook containing list of court cases, n.d., 15 pages. MsV. 28. (Box 12)
  - Notebook containing an index of names, n.d., 7 pages. MsV. 29. (Box 12)
  - Statement of money received from Writ Taxes by James B. Edwards, 1803-1808., 22 pages. MsV. 30. (Box 12)